Off. Alright, today's דף, daf, we are going to see if we
can complete דף ל Daf Lamed but we pick up on the
middle of כ''ט ע''ב, Kaf Tes Amud Beis, and we are up
to the following:
לימא כתנאי. Leima Ketannai. It is top of כ''ט ע''ב, Kaf Tes
Amud Beis, six lines down, line starts with the word כתנאי. Ketannai.
So this debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish about whether the נזירות nezirut that a father can make his
son a נזיר nazir is a special הלכה halacha by נזירות nezirut
that the father has this power, this ability to impose it on
his son, or whether it's all דרבנן derabbanan and it's some type
of a form of חינוך chinuch and in the process of this
חינוך, chinuch, allows us to skirt or to compromise a lot of
other principles, so it's quite fascinating. So the גמרא Gemara says let's
say this is tied, this is parallel a debate of תנאים, Tannaim,
or it is a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. And here's the ברייתא:
braita: עד מתי מדיר בנו בנזיר? Ad masai madzir beno benazir? To
what age can a father make his son a נזיר? nazir? עד
שיביא שתי שערות דברי רבי, Ad sheyavi shtei se'aros, divrei Rabbi, until
he brings two pubic hairs, until he's a בר מצוה, bar mitzvah,
meaning plus the age of thirteen, that's implicit. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
אומר עד שיגיע לעונת נדרים, Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda omer ad sheyagi'a
le'onot nedarim, until he comes to the stage of making vows. Something
that we have not really fully explored yet is that a child,
boy or girl, a year before their age of majority, a year
before a girl's בת מצוה bat mitzvah and a year before a
boy's בר מצוה bar mitzvah can make a vow and it's binding
if the person understands what the sort of you know the meaning
of the vow, you know, that they're making a vow to God
and they have basic understanding of what they're doing. That's considered a
מופלא סמוך לאיש, Mufla Samuch l'Ish, the מופלא Mufla from the word
להפליא, lehafli, to enunciate, to create a vow before a person is
actually an adult. So it's a very fascinating area of
הלכה, halacha, and again there's a question there: is it דאורייתא d'oraisa
or דרבנן? derabbanan? We're about to sort of see some of that
in a minute.
So one person says if you are doing the vow for your
son, you can only do it until the age that your son
is of the age of making vows himself, which is this year
of עונת נדרים. onot nedarim. So the גמרא Gemara says, well let's
take a look. מאי לאו תנאי היא? Mai lav Tannai hi? Isn't
this the debate of תנאים, Tannaim, our debate? דרבי סבר הלכה בנזיר,
DeRabbi savar halacha benazir, רבי Rabbi holds that it's the ability for
a power to do a for a father to do it on
his son is a special הלכה, halacha, it's like a הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, it's this biblical power that he has, we
don't have a basis for it in the verses but this is
just a special power that he has as it were for his
son as long as the son is a minor, as long as
the son is sort of under the auspices of the father. ואף
על גב דהגיע לעונת נדרים, Ve'af al gav dehigi'a le'onot nedarim, and
although why should it matter that the son is of the age
of נדרים? nedarim? This is an ability the father has for his
son as long as the son is still considered a minor,
עד שיביא שתי שערות, ad sheyavi shtei se'aros, until he becomes an
adult. So even though the son is maybe to some degree an
adult in terms of he can make his own vows, but this
is about the father's power, as it were, over the son, and
the son is still considered a minor. ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה דאמר
עד שיגיע לעונת נדרים, VeRabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda d'amar ad sheyagi'a le'onot
nedarim, and according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda
that says that the principle is, and here it's רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda, yesterday we quoted רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
it was questioned whether we're referring to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda or רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Chanina,
anyway in this ברייתא braita it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose
b'Rebbi Yehuda who says that until he's the age of twelve, סבר
כדי
לחנכו במצות, savar kedei lechancho bemitzvot, his approach would be consistent with
the idea that the power of the father to do this is
a form of
חינוך. chinuch. וכיון דנפיק מרשותיה, Ve'kivan denafik merishutei, once the son is
outside the father's control, תו לא מחייב, tu lo mechayev, he's no
longer obligated. Now again, it's not exactly clear, what does that mean
out of the father's control? I mean he's still a minor, he's
still in all other areas or whatever in general he's not let's
say obligated for his transgressions, maybe and isn't you know but nevertheless
it's understanding that the idea of חינוך chinuch in an area relating
to vows and נזיר nazir is less relevant when the child is
empowered to do it himself. חינוך chinuch is the idea that the
father is going to train the child and the child means that
the child is not yet sort of you know an agent in
that area himself. Once the child can sort of do it himself,
so look, you know there's plenty of things that even once you're
an adult, you know you could help to have a little people
a little advice, a little training, a little guidance in a lot
of areas of life, okay, but nevertheless, point is is that if
it's about חינוך chinuch and in this particular area the child is
no longer a minor in this area, then חינוך chinuch is no
longer relevant, okay, or is
no that would
not be something that the father would be empowered. Okay, but again
it's not a clear line up because you could you know you
could be because as I say it's not black and white that
it would divide along those lines which is what the גמרא Gemara
is going to. Yeah, I understand, but the point is דנפיק מרשותיה
denafik merishutei in a limited way because in all other areas he's
not. So if it's not about חינוך, chinuch, if it's just straight
about the father's ability to impose it on the kid, right, so
who cares if the kid can do it himself? The father has
this ability and he's looking at the thing in a big picture,
the kid's still a minor. But if it's specifically about חינוך chinuch
and in this particular area the kid is no longer a minor
in this area, then חינוך chinuch is no longer relevant,
okay. Say. אמר ליה לא, amar lei lo, no, that's not necessarily
the division. I could go either way here. דכולי עלמא הלכה היא
בנזיר. d'chulei alma halacha hi b'Nazir. First of all, I could say
that everybody says it's a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. והכא
במופלא סמוך לאיש קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'mufla samuch l'ish kamifligi. The debate is
what status you give this idea of somebody who is a מופלא
mufla who can enunciate vows, who's legally able to create vows but
is not yet an adult. רבי סבר מופלא סמוך לאיש דרבנן. Rabbi
savar mufla samuch l'ish d'rabbanan.
רבי Rabbi holds that that whole category is a דרבנן d'rabbanan category.
Again, similar to the question of can a father make his son
a נזיר Nazir is also a similar question about when a person
makes vows an age before adulthood, is that binding biblically or not
or is it only rabbinic? Right? All these areas where you know
the גמרא Gemara could ask similar questions. I don't understand. How could
that be binding rabbinic? Would you give the guy lashes if he
was 12 years old or a girl 11 and made a vow
and then violated it? You know, similar types of questions where we're
going to act as if it's biblical but the whole thing might
really be rabbinic. So the same way we're sort of saying that
by the father making his son a נזיר, Nazir, there're similar questions
about this idea about making vows a year before adulthood. So רבי
Rabbi could be of the opinion that that whole category is rabbinic.
ואתי דאורייתא דחי דרבנן. v'ati d'oraisa dachi d'rabbanan.
And therefore the biblical way that the father is empowered to impose
נזירות nezirus on the son, assuming it's a הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha
l'Moshe m'Sinai,
obviously overrides any דרבנן d'rabbanan independence that the son might have in
the area of vows. That's only some דרבנן d'rabbanan status. So that
would be the opinion that the father could do it because the
whole independence that the son has at the age of 12 is
only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה סבר מופלא סמוך לאיש דאורייתא.
Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda savar mufla samuch l'ish d'oraisa. No,
it's דאורייתא d'oraisa and therefore even if it's not based on חינוך,
chinuch, even if it's based on הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai,
nevertheless,
if the son is an independent agent in the matter of vows,
then even then the father is then since a נזירות nezirus is
a vow, even if it's not based on חינוך, chinuch, the father
shouldn't be able to impose it on the son. Okay, so as
opposed to before that somehow we thought if it was הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, then it wouldn't matter that the son is
independent in this area because big picture the son is still a
minor. Here the גמרא's Gemara saying no, even if it's not based
on חינוך, chinuch, why should the father be able to impose this
on the son if in this area, the area of
נדרים, nedarim, the son is independent? So the father he should be
out of the father's רשות reshus even not through a חינוך chinuch
lens, but just in a sense of a power like lens. If
the son is empowered, the father should not be empowered. But that
would only be if the idea of מופלא סמוך לאיש mufla samuch
l'ish is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. If the son has this independence at a
דאורייתא d'oraisa level. If he only has it at a דרבנן d'rabbanan
level, then the father can still go ahead and impose נזירות nezirus
on the son.
Yes, הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai is always considered הלכה halacha
to be דאורייתא d'oraisa level.
Yes, I mean look, הלכה halacha okay, תפילין tefillin for example and
other things.
Yes, yes, so
this גמרא Gemara clearly assumes that הלכה halacha means דאורייתא, d'oraisa, but
there are two questions on that which I should sort of mention.
One is that there are times הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai
is used more rhetorically, metaphorically, not literally and but right, exactly
and does not really mean דאורייתא, d'oraisa, but really means like it's
like a, you know, I mean anyway, there's a classic example that
there's a משנה Mishnah says הלכה עמון ומואב מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית,
halacha Amon u'Moav me'asrin ma'asar ani b'shevi'is, a משנה Mishnah in עדיות,
Eduyos, where basically it's talking about a דרבנן d'rabbanan obligation of the
lands outside of Israel to take תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'ma'asros, it's clearly
דרבנן d'rabbanan and he uses the phrase הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai. So there are times when it's not used literally.
Actually Christine Hayes, a scholar in Yale, has a, I think Yale,
right? Yeah, anyway, she's got a whole good article on the development
of the concept of הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, so that
when it you know, might, you know, and what it might have
meant at different stages in terms
of of the Tannaitic and and Talmudic period. That's point number one.
Point number two is the גמרא Gemara never said הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. I was waiting for somebody to call me on
this. The גמרא Gemara just said הלכה. halacha. Now there's a general
assumption that the word הלכה halacha means הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai, but there is actually some question about that, that whether הלכה
halacha might actually mean I think there's a נצי"ב Netziv that says
that הלכה halacha in רש"י Rashi whatever, he he I'm not remembering
the specifics, but he basically says הלכה halacha might just mean it's
an ancient tradition that doesn't have the same meaning as הלכה למשה
מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. The point though here is that the גמרא
Gemara is clearly assuming that the position of הלכה halacha means דאורייתא.
d'oraisa. You know, that's clearly coming up in this dynamics. If it's
a הלכה, halacha, then it would override a דרבנן d'rabbanan status that
the son has, but you know, but it wouldn't override a דאורייתא
d'oraisa status that the son has. So here it's clearly assumed that
הלכה halacha means that. Now the difference here might be that often
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai is some independent law, like you
know here, it's telling you a parameter within the דאורייתא d'oraisa laws
of נזירות. nezirus. So as if you just said some new thing
is a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai or הלכה, halacha, maybe
you don't mean it goes back to משה, Moshe, maybe you don't
mean it's דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But here what we're saying is this is
something that we always knew was part of the parameters of נזירות,
nezirus, so ultimately. is folded in to a דאורייתא d'Oraitha דין. din.
Correct. So it might be different here because you're dealing with something
that's already a דאורייתא d'Oraitha category.
Giving you more detail on what that דאורייתא.
d'Oraitha. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So anyway, so if the so could be that everybody agrees that
the idea that a father makes a son a נזיר nazir is
not based on a rabbinic concept of חנוך, chinuch, it's part of
the laws of נזירות. nezirut. Would it override a son who is
twelve and can make his own vows? Well, if that's a status
of independence that the תורה Torah recognizes, then the father would lose
control in that case. If it's only a rabbinic status of independence,
then the father would still have control in that case. So that's
version number one.
What if the מופלא mufla is דאורייתא d'Oraitha and the son has
considered independent counsel on his own, would the father have the opportunity
to מתיר matir the נדר neder of the son?
No, there's no oh you mean because of קרובים? krovim? I mean
yeah, I mean a קרוב karov can be מתיר matir a נדר.
neder. You mean מתיר matir or you mean to be מיפר? meifer?
There's no הפרה. hafara. No, there's no הפרה. hafara. הפרה's hafara only
husband and wife. Or no, father and daughter, not father and son.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so that's one approach. Okay,
ואיבעית
אימא, v'ibaiteima, another approach, דכולי עלמא כדי לחנכו במצוות. d'chulei alma k'dei
l'chancho b'mitzvot.
Everybody agrees it's from a חנוך chinuch perspective and it's all rabbinic.
ומופלא סמוך לאיש דרבנן. u'mufla samuch l'ish d'rabbanan. And the idea of
מופלא mufla is דרבנן, d'rabbanan, because if it was biblical, then if
the son had independence, it was דאורייתא-speaking d'Oraitha independent, it would be
bizarre that the father could impose חנוך chinuch over the son when
his status was fully independent even from the תורה's Torah perspective. But
here what you have is two דרבנןs d'rabbanan running up against one
another. That the חנוך chinuch is a rabbinic responsibility of the father
and the son has
rabbinic independence as well. So how is those going to so which
one is going to win out? Okay, ומופלא סמוך לאיש דרבנן. u'mufla
samuch l'ish d'rabbanan. רבי סבר אתי חנוך דרבנן ודחי מופלא סמוך לאיש
דרבנן. Rabbi savar ati chinuch d'rabbanan v'dachi mufla samuch l'ish d'rabbanan. Fine.
So now though we will give more weight to the father's role
of חנוך. chinuch. We'll say the son's independence is only דרבנן, d'rabbanan,
the father's obligation of חנוך chinuch is דרבנן. d'rabbanan. In this case,
we're going to tip in favor of the father's role as חנוך
chinuch and we're going to let the father still continue to make
the son a נזיר. nazir. And we're also obviously, I mean we're
already compromising so many other laws in terms of חולין בעזרה chullin
ba'azarah and, you know, and שחיטה לעוף, shechitah l'of, so we'll also
override the son's independence. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה דאמר עד שיגיע לעונת
נדרים Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda d'amar ad she'yavi l'onash nedarim says
no, once the son is ראוי roy to make vows, קסבר לא
אתי חנוך דרבנן ודחי מופלא סמוך לאיש. kasavar lo ati chinuch d'rabbanan
v'dachi mufla samuch l'ish. No, once the rabbis made the son recognize
the son's independence and the role of נדרים, nedarim, even at the
age of twelve, so that also took him out of the category
of חנוך. chinuch. Okay. So you cannot link it in to this
question about the age whether it goes by thirteen or whether it
goes by twelve because that would that could still depend that could
work either way based on whether the question of what's biblical and
what's rabbinic. And even if it is based if it's based on
חנוך chinuch certainly once the son has independence, חנוך chinuch might be
the father might not have a role of חנוך. chinuch. But who
knows, maybe the rabbis sort of did away with the son's independence
to allow חנוך chinuch in this area. Or even if it's a
הלכה, halakha, and even if it's דאורייתא, d'Oraitha, the son's independent if
the son's independence is a biblical idea as well at that age
of twelve, then the father's power would be would not extend in
that case even if it weren't based on חנוך. chinuch. Yes.
Same thing in the particularity of נזירות nezirut חנוך chinuch and can
know who's doing it for and the rabbis empower him and that
kind of a case and that'll apply, but let's say he's younger
and really doesn't know what he's doing.
No,
it wouldn't matter. But we'll get to עונת נדרים, onash nedarim, but
no, you need both criteria. Same way you need thirteen and two
pubic hairs, you need twelve and to know what you're doing. It's
the combination of years and knowledge.
Yes. סמוך לאיש samuch l'ish means סמוך לפרקו. samuch l'pirko. In other
words, yes, סמוך samuch close to being adultus.
Correct. Okay. לימא הני תנאי כהני תנאי. neima hani tannayei k'hani tannayei.
Okay,
how about the following תנאים? tannaim? That we just quoted two תנאים
tannaim that debate whether it's thirteen or twelve. Let's say it's linked
to the following תנאים tannaim that also debate if it's thirteen or
twelve, and there's actually a funny statement because it's not just these
are like these, actually the same תנאים, tannaim, it's רבי Rabbi and
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda, so it's a
strange intro, but okay. דתניא detanya we taught a ברייתא. baraita. מעשה
ברבי חנינא, maaseh b'Rabbi Chanina, there was רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, שהזיר
אביו נזיר, she'hizir aviv nazir, his father made him a נזיר. nazir.
You see, the גמרא's Gemara not making the משנה's Mishna not making
this stuff up, this stuff happened. והביאו לפני רבן גמליאל, vehevilo lifnei
Rabban Gamliel, and they brought him in front of רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel to figure out like what's he going to do now, the
נזירות's nezirut over, bring a קרבן. korban. היה רבן גמליאל בודק בו
לדעת אם הביא שתי שערות אם לא הביא. hayah Rabban Gamliel bodek
bo ladaat im heivi shtei searot im lo heivi. And רבן גמליאל's
Rabban Gamliel trying to figure out, did he bring two pubic hairs
or not? Was he an adult? So when a father made him
a נזיר, nazir, was his father able to make him a נזיר?
nazir? Maybe the kid was an adult at that time and the
father's act of making him a נזירות nezirut would not work. So
אם לא הביא. im lo heivi. So that's the first position. רבי
יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says, no,
no, no. The question wasn't whether the father did it when the
kid was whether the kid was בר מצווה Bar Mitzvah or not.
The question was לדעת אם הגיע לעונת נדרים אם לאו. ladaat im
higia l'onash nedarim im lav. He wanted to know if the kid
had gotten to the age of vows or not. The age of
making vows a year before בר מצוה *bar mitzvah*, which means to
check, presumably the age of the kid was known. So in one
version the kid was thirteen and the question was did he have
two pubic hairs? That would determine if he was an adult. The
other case, the kid was twelve and the question was did he
know how he was, you know, to what פסק *pesak* he was
making vows or not? So that would be the other requirement in
addition to age that is required for this status of עונת נדרים
onath nedarim *onat nedarim*. So that's the debate, did the father have
the power to do it? So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel? *Rabban Gamliel*
was trying to figure that out and the question was: either was
the kid thirteen with two pubic hairs or was the kid twelve
and knowing and knew how to make vows. And if that was
true, the father did not have the power to do it. Okay,
so, okay, אם לאו *im lav*. אמר לו *amar lo*. So רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina, *Rabbi Chanina* said to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel. *Rabban
Gamliel*, his I guess his name at that stage was just חנינא
Chanina *Chanina*. Okay, said to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel? *Rabban Gamliel*. אמר
לו *amar lo*. רבי *Rabbi*, אל תצטער בבחינתי *al tista'er bevichinati*. You
know what, you don't have to bother checking me. אם קטן אני
*im katan ani* אהיה בשביל אבא *eheye bishvil aba*. Look, if I
was a minor when my father did imposed נזירות neziros, *nezirut* on
me, fine, I'm a נזיר nazir *nazir* because of what my father
did. אם גדול אני *im gadol ani* אהיה בשביל עצמי *eheye bishvil
atzmi*. I accept נזירות neziros *nezirut* on myself now anyway. So look,
I'll save you the trouble, either way I'll be a נזיר nazir
*nazir*. So the kid was a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*. Yeah, so
I think he was הגיע לעונת נדרים *higia le'onat nedarim*. Okay. עמד
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel ונשקו על ראשו *amad Rabban Gamliel venashko al
rosho*. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*, what? Hold on, רבן גמליאל
*Rabban Gamliel* stood up and kissed him on his head. אמר לו
*amar lo* I mean, said, מובטח אני בזה שיורה הלכה halacha. בישראל
*muvtach ani beze sheyoreh halacha beyisrael*. Oh, such a תלמיד חכם *talmid
chacham*. I know that this young man will eventually be a teacher
of הלכה halacha. *halacha* in Israel. אמרו לו *amru lo* היו ימים
ואתי *hayu yamim va'ati* it was not a long time, עד שהורה
הלכה halacha בישראל *ad shehoreh halacha beyisrael* until it actually came true
and he grew up to be a big תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*
and a רבי *rabbi* and he taught הלכה halakhah *halacha* in Israel.
Now, so here we have this question again, the same question about
whether it is thirteen or twelve. Now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* has
a question. בשלמא *beshalma* לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *leRabbi Yosi beRabbi Yehuda*
or לרבי יוסי *leRabbi Yosi*, again this whole question of which רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yoseis *Rabbi Yosi* is this, דאמר *de'amar* עד שיגיע לעונת
נדרים *ad sheyagia le'onat nedarim*, היינו דקאמר *hayinu dekamar* אם קטן אני
אהיה בשביל אבא *im katan ani eheye bishvil aba*. So we get
it, he's saying look, if I'm a minor then it'll be my
father and if not I'll do it myself because I'm הגיע לעונת
נדרים *higia le'onat nedarim*. This question is not going to be a
real question, the רא"ש Rosh *Rosh* says we're just sort of getting,
asking this throwaway question to get to the next question. But anyway,
here's the question. אלא *ela* לרבי *leRabbi* דאמר *de'amar* עד שיביא שתי
שערות *ad sheyavi shtei se'arot* according to רבי *Rabbi* that says that
it's until he is an adult and brings two pubic hairs, ואם
גדול אני אהיה בשביל עצמי *ve'im gadol ani eheye bishvil atzmi* and
he's saying if I'm an adult I'll be for myself, הא ברשותיה
דאבוה קאי *ha birshutei de'avuah ka'iyam*. He's still in his father's control.
Now what the heck do you mean? He says if I'm an
adult means if I'm thirteen and have two pubic hairs and I'm
an adult. So the רא"ש Rosh, *Rosh* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
for some somehow bizarrely thinks that even though רבי *Rabbi* says that
the test was to see if he was an adult and had
two pubic hairs, when the kid חנינא *Chanina* said "if I'm an
adult" it meant if I've gotten to עונת נדרים onath nedarim, *onat
nedarim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying well why is it
enough that he got to עונת נדרים *onat nedarim* if according to
רבי *Rabbi* he needs to actually be a full adult? But I
mean it's a silly question because the answer is no, what he
meant was "if I'm an adult" so according to רבי *Rabbi* who
says it's about being thirteen and two pubic hairs, that's what he
was saying, he wasn't saying עונת נדרים *onat nedarim*. So the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* says fine. אלא דאמר אהיה בשביל אבא אהיה בשביל עצמי
*ela de'amar eheye bishvil aba eheye bishvil atzmi* okay fine, but what
you're saying is I get it's like it's hard to know what
the question is, it's hard to see the answer, but the basic
point was no no no, even according to רבי *Rabbi* he means
either if I am, it doesn't mean if, if according to רבי
*Rabbi* that the test was to see if he was an adult
or not, if he had two pubic hairs, so that's what the
kid was saying, if I'm not an adult then I'll be for
my father and if I'm an adult and I'm thirteen with two
pubic hairs I'll be for myself. Fine, that was like a throwaway
question. Here's really our question. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: אי אייתי שתי שערות מעיקרא *i ayiti shtei se'arot me'ikara* look
says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* fine, let's take a look from the
perspective of the thirteen, whether it's the twelve or the thirteen it
doesn't matter, but here's our question. If he had two pubic hairs
from before when the father made him a נזיר nazir *nazir*, קאי
בנזירות דיליה *kai binezirut dilei*. I'm sorry, then yes, when the father
made him a נזיר Nazir, *nazir* and then קאי בנזירות דיליה *kai
binezirut dilei*, then the fact that he basically the father made him
a נזיר Nazir *nazir*, he was already an adult, but he maybe
silently acquiesced, maybe he even verbally said yes or something of that
nature, then fine, then he's his own נזיר Nazir, *nazir*, that we
understand. ובסוף *ubesof* קאי בנזירות
דאבוה *kai binezirut de'avuah*.
One minute. Oh, I, ובסוף
*ubesof*. If he had only the two hairs at the end, he
went, he was a minor when the father did it, he spent
the thirty days, and after the thirty days was over then the
kid became an adult, that also we understand the case, קאי בנזירות
דאבוה *kai binezirut de'avuah*, then it would be the father. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says look, when did he become an adult?
There are three possible scenarios: he was already an adult when the
father did it, he was an adult after the end of the
נזירות neziros. *nezirut*, or he became an adult in the middle. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says we're going to have to figure out
that last case. Because the first two cases are easy. If he
was an adult when the father did it, then it was his
own, somehow his silent acquiescence or maybe he verbally said yes, he's
fine, we can understand he's his own נזיר Nazir *nazir* and it's
done after thirty days. If he became an adult after the thirty
days was over it's also done at the end of the thirty
days, that's what the father did. But what happens if... He became
an adult in the middle, right? And we're going to assume, and
this is by the way not explicit in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
but it's explicit in the תוספתא *Tosefta*, that if the father makes
his son a נזיר nazir *nazir* and in the middle of the
30 days the son becomes an adult, that's sort of like the
case in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* where the son protests. Remember the
case of the son or the relatives protesting or shaving? Once he
reached an age where he now is independent, that terminates the father's
נזירות neziros *neziros* even if he doesn't do anything, just by virtue
of becoming an adult. So if that's true and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* sort of assumes that, we have how could the, how could
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina *Rebbi Chanina* or they state, let's say חנינא
*Chanina* say, hey don't worry, either way I'm a נזיר nazir *nazir*.
It's not true either way you're a נזיר nazir *nazir*. You're a
נזיר nazir *nazir* if you only became an adult at the end
of 30 days or if you became an adult or you were
already an adult at the beginning. But if you became an adult
sometime in the middle, right, let's say רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* was
checking him on day ten, right? So if he only became an
adult then on day ten, so he would need 30 days from
that point onwards because becoming an adult in the middle would have
interrupted the period that had preceded, right?
So it just ended,
right, ended, meaning, yeah, he'd
have to do 30 days
unless he wanted to accept it upon himself, right, and if what
חנינא *Chanina* was saying was I accept it upon myself regardless, right,
fine, you accept it upon yourself, but then it needs to be
30 days from this point, not you can't just say either way
30 days from the outset here.
You guys also get to the question of when did he become
a גדול *gadol*. If you're talking about it wasn't on the same
day that the father made him a נזיר nazir.
*nazir*, then he didn't accept a נזירות neziros? *neziros* when he became
a גדול *gadol*.
Right, he didn't accept נזירות neziros. *neziros* when he came to,
exactly, exactly, so maybe he hasn't even been a נזיר nazir *nazir*
all together, exactly.
And נזירות neziros *neziros* doesn't really end, it just dissipates or disappears.
It doesn't have to bring a,
right, it doesn't end naturally, it's sort of like when the husband
annuls his wife's vows or like, or like the case of מיכה
*Micha* in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, correct. So that's the גמרא'ס *Gemara's*
question. ואי איצטריך במיצעא מאי mai? *Ve'i itzterich bemitzei'a mai*? But if
it comes in the middle, what would be the story then? הניחא
לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה דאמר עד שיבואו לעונת נדרים *Hani'cha le'Rebbi Yose
beRebbi Yehuda de'amar ad she'yavo'u le'onat nedarim*. Now somehow the גמרא'ס *Gemara's*
going to think this is easier if we're thinking about עונת נדרים
*onat nedarim*. דאמר עד שיבואו לעונת נדרים *De'amar ad she'yavo'u le'onat nedarim*.
אלא לרבי דאמר עד שיביא שתי שערות מאי איכא למימר *Ela le'Rebbi
de'amar ad she'yavi shtei se'arot mai ika lemeimar*? So what's, now why
is it easier if it's an issue about עונת נדרים *onat nedarim*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to assume, because remember that תוספתא
*Tosefta* I mentioned says when the kid becomes an adult it interrupts
it in the middle, okay, that or interrupts it or ends it
in the middle, that that would only be the case of שתי
שערות *shtei se'arot*. That if, because that's really a biblical status of
being an adult and that really breaks the נזירות neziros *neziros* from
before. But if it's the issue about עונת נדרים *onat nedarim*, so
there we could say look, since the father was entitled to impose
it at the beginning, right, whether that's based on חינוך chinuch, *chinuch*
or whether that's based on well, actually the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes
that if it's עונת נדרים *onat nedarim* it's within the world of
חינוך chinuch, *chinuch* or whatever, anyway if the father's entitled, well no,
maybe not, forget. And if the father's whatever empowered either for חינוך
*chinuch* or just because that's the הלכה halakhah *halacha* to impose it,
then the fact that the kid has asserted a certain amount of
independence in the area of נדרים *nedarim* is not strong enough to
change his status. That's only a limited ability to make vows for
himself. So if he already started as a נזיר Nazir, *nazir* because
the father was able to impose it at the beginning of the
process, עונת נדרים *onat nedarim* would not interrupt that, would not end
that. Okay, what would end it is that you've completely changed your
legal status. If you've gone from being a minor to being an
adult, then even if you were in the middle of some process
that your father had begun, you're now a completely new legal status
and it would end. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now, so
that's the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* question. We got a question if the idea
is being a, is being בר מצווה bar mitzvah *bar mitzvah*, being
an adult. That should completely end the נזירות neziros *neziros* that a
father imposed earlier. If it's עונת נדרים *onat nedarim*, it's very nice
that now you're able to do certain ex, you know, now you're
able to make your own vows, but you're in the middle of
a vow that your father imposed on you. That doesn't end, your
basic legal status is the same. Okay, if you had that independence
at the beginning, your father couldn't have imposed the vow. But now
that your father did impose the vow, it's not going to, that
process isn't going to end just because you can do it yourself.
Okay, so that's the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* assumption. הניחא לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
דאמר עד שיבואו לעונת נדרים *Hani'cha le'Rebbi Yose beRebbi Yehuda de'amar ad
she'yavo'u le'onat nedarim*. According to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *Rebbi Yose beRebbi
Yehuda* that it's about an age of making vows, the fact that
you got to that age that now you can make your own
vows doesn't stop a נזירות nezirus *neziros* that your father imposed. אלא
לרבי דאמר עד שיביא שתי שערות מאי איכא למימר *Ela le'Rebbi de'amar
ad she'yavi shtei se'arot mai ika lemeimar*? But רבי *Rebbi* who says
that it's about being an adult,
when you become an adult your previous status should completely end from
what your father did, you're completely now a new legal status, you
shouldn't be held by that. So that whole נזירות nezirus *neziros* ends.
So the argument is exactly the opposite.
I understand, but let's work with the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמרי לרבי לא קשיא כאן דאזיל ליה וכאן
דאבוי *Amri le'Rebbi lo kashya kan de'azil lei vekan de'avui*. You're right,
according to רבי *Rebbi* you would not necessarily be able to say
it doesn't matter ממה נפשך mimah nafshach *mima nafshach*, it's 30 days
from the outset. It's not necessarily 30 days from the outset if
he became an adult in the middle, then it would not be
from the outset. So for רבי *Rebbi* it would have to be
both the father's 30 days from the outset and 30 days from
the time he became an adult. So therefore if you wanted to
play it safe and I don't know when I became an adult,
but I'm saying to you right now that if I'm an adult
right now, but actually it wouldn't work because you could
say if... but maybe I'll become an adult ten days from now.
So basically, what he would have to do is he would have
to like wait till the end of 30 days, the end of
30 days and then say, if I was a, let's see. If
I'm not an adult now, then I'm not doing anything, right? And
I finished the נזירות nezirus, of my father and I finished 30
days. But if I דוקא dafka became an adult today, on day
30, or on day 29, or whatever it was, so I didn't
complete my נזירות, nezirus then I'm accepting a new נזירות nezirus now
starting today and then 30 days from now he would bring a
קרבן korban because then ממה נפשך he'd done one נזירות. nezirus Yes,
Charlie.
And in the case of רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, he would not
have had a conventional way to end the נזירות nezirus because he
would have had after the destruction of Temple.
That what? רבי חנינא's, Rabbi Chaninas. it was a generation after רבן
גמליאל?
Right, he was a generation after רבן גמליאל.
What about רבן גמליאל?
רבן גמליאל lived after the destruction of Temple.
Wait, how do you know which רבן גמליאל we're talking about?
Well, but רבן... well רבי חנינא lived... was a contemporary of רבי
יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi.
Oh, was he? Okay, I'll trust you on that. I don't have
the generations straight. But okay.
I was going to ask if this is the same... possibly the
same חנינא as יוסי בר...
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא.
Rabbi Yosei b'rebbi
Chanina.
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Rabbi Yosei b'rebbi Chanina, yeah, so that's... I
don't know either. That's part, I think, that... I don't know. Right.
And if so, it has something
to do with all the accommodation, yeah, right.
You know who you're talking about... רבי חנינא, that's a...
you know, I know there's like two רבי יוסי floating around, and
there's a רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yosei b'rebbi Chanina floating around.
Right, yeah, I don't know. What does Wikipedia say or whoever?
Well, there are a bunch of רבי חנינא.
Yeah, a whole bunch.
Yeah. I'm not sure that we can assume this is post-Temple.
Is the logic of this argument similar to גיור קטן giur katan
where he reaches
גיל מצוות gil mitzvos and it just kind of goes away unless
he affirms it?
Something. I mean there's some idea that it was something, a status
that was imposed and then an ability... it's not exactly the same
but there's definitely similarity. It's also similar to a question like a
very famous question the מנחת חינוך Minchas Chinuch has, he has a
lot of fun with this. Somebody is, which actually happens like a
good 15% of the time, kid becomes בר מצווה bar mitzvah in
the middle of the ספירה. Sefirah. Right, so does the מצווה mitzvah
of counting the rest of the ספירה, Sefirah, is that דאורייתא de'oraisa
or not? Because does the counting he did pre-בר מצווה bar mitzvah
enough to frame the continued counting as part of a process of
counting 50 days, or do we say it was completely meaningless?
It's a פשט, peshat, I don't remember here in this גמרא.
Gemara Yeah, it would have been relevant. Alright, let's move on. Anyway,
that's the end of that סוגיא, sugya, but it is interesting the
idea that even if
that... the question about when the father can do it, if the
kid is בר מצווה bar mitzvah, or the kid is 12, is
not necessarily the same of what stage would end it. בר מצווה,
which is a complete independent status, legally independent status, would end it,
if it was imposed by the father, whereas עונת נדרים would not
be... the father wouldn't be able to impose it when maybe at
עונת נדרים, but it would not be strong enough to end it.
Okay, yes.
Does anybody bring in the concept of whether he has the right
to object when he first becomes aware of it as an adult?
Yeah, well that's the משנה. Mishnah, The משנה Mishnah. says that the
kid can object.
Previous משנה, Mishnah but not here in this case.
Well you don't even have to object.
If he becomes aware or עונה ona in the middle, can he
at that point can he end the נזירות? nezirus.
Yes, that's implicit in the משנה. Mishnah, The משנה Mishnah. says that
if the kid objects or the relatives object that that... it ends
the נזירות. nezirus So this is that being an adult ends it
even without him objecting, but even as a minor he can object
and it ends. That was... the גמרא didn't explore that part of
the משנה, Mishnah but that was explicit in the משנה. Mishnah.
I thought he had
to
be... The משנה Mishnah. said that he or the relatives can object
and it ends it. Now there is a
question תוספות Tosafos raises whether... whether the objecting has to be immediate
or not, okay, so that was... that's not spelled out in the
משנה. Mishnah What? I have no idea. Let's move on. All right,
next משנה. Mishnah האיש מגלח על נזירות אביו ואין האישה מגלחת על
נזירות אביה. Ha'ish megalai'ach al neziros aviv v'ein ha'ishah megalachas al neziros
aviah. Okay,
so here's another father-son thing, but not the son as a minor.
Here's a case that we saw earlier where the father accepts נזירות
nezirus and then the father dies and he left over money, can
the son become a נזיר Nazir, and use the money that the
father left over? So the point in this משנה Mishnah, is a
son can do it, but not a daughter. So once again, very
much father-son.
כיצד, Keitzad, how is this? מי שהיה אביו נזיר והפריש מעות סתומים
על נזירותו ומת, Mi shehaya aviv nazir v'hifrish ma'os setumim al neziroso
umes, somebody whose father was a נזיר and he set aside unspecified
funds for his נזירות nezirut and then he dies, ואמר, v'amar,
and then the son said, הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח על מעות
אבא. hareni nazir al menas she'agalai'ach al ma'os abba. I am going
to be a נזיר but... so he accepted the נזירות Neziros. after
the father died and on the stipulation that he gets to use
the funds that the father left over. father had set aside. Now
remember, normally those funds would go to an עולה. olah. It's this
magic pile of unspecified funds, which has a certain amount of flexibility
what's going to happen with it. So here one of the חידוש
chiddush is that in a normal case it goes to an עולה,
olah, but if the son at that stage accepts נזירות Neziros on
the stipulation to use the funds, he gets to use them for
his קרבנות. korbanos. Okay. הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח על מעות
אבא. Hareini nazir al m'nas she'agale'ach al ma'os abba. So Rabbi Yossi,
הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה, Harei elu yiplu lindava, ah, says Rabbi Yossi,
if however he did it after the father died, then the money
goes as what we normally say goes with those funds, it goes
to an עולה. olah. אם אין זה מגלח על נזירות אביו, Im
ein ze m'galei'ach al nezirus aviv, and that is not the case
of somebody that gets to use the father's money. איזהו שמגלח על
נזירות אביו, Eizehu she'megalei'ach al nezirus aviv, who's the case of somebody
who gets to use the father's money? Not when he accepts the
נזירות neziros after the father died, but מי שהיה הוא ואביו נזירים,
Mi she'haya hu v'aviv nezirim, he and his father were נזירים nezirim
at the same time, והפריש אביו מעות סתומים לנזירותו, V'hifrish aviv maos
stumim l'neziroso, and
the father set aside funds for the father's נזירות, neziros ומת, U'meis,
and the father died. זהו שמגלח על נזירות אביו, Zehu she'megalei'ach al
nezirus aviv, that's the one that gets to use the father's money.
Now that seems a little bit more strange, because if he and
the father were נזירים nezirim at the same time, then his נזירות
neziros never explicitly stipulated the ability to use those funds, and for
the first 29 days of the נזירות neziros? he was assuming he
would have to use his own funds, and somehow the point was
when he and according to this approach, when he and the father
are נזירים nezirim at the same time, they're somehow seen as somehow
sharing, doing it not as two independent parties, but somehow if it's
the son and father doing it together, and maybe this follows the
previous idea, the father imposes the נזירות neziros on the son, it
seems like it's a family activity. So I'm serious, that's the point,
yeah, since they're doing it at the same time it's a family
activity, so if the father dies, the funds get transferred to the
son, but if the son did it after the father died, then
it's not a family activity, then he's just an independent person, he
can't use the father's money. So two different approaches: one is he
דווקא davka gets to use it if he did it after the
father died, because then his נזירות nezirus from the beginning stipulated that
he'd use those moneys, and those moneys were already in a state
that they were somewhat a little indeterminate what was going to be
with that. And the other approach is no, only if he was
doing it participating together with his father as a family activity, then
do the funds get transferred to him.
Or what, wait, so
I have two questions: one is if the father died on day
29, the son has one day or 31?
No, one day, it's the son, no, one day. One day, yeah,
okay, right.
And why isn't the second model more of a ירושה yerusha model?
It's a ירושה, yerusha, right?
Yeah, it is, but you don't ירש yerish money that, yeah, money
for the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, father sets aside money for any
other קרבן, korban, you don't have a right to use it for
your own קרבנות. korbanos.
Exactly, right, exactly, if you made that decision. Exactly, right.
And the גמרא's going to get to how much does it follow,
but normal ירושה yerusha wouldn't cover it because this is money that's
sanctified for a קרבן. korban. But it's within that type of concept,
it's a special allowance in the case of נזירות. nezirus That is
correct. Yeah.
Two unrelated people are נזירים, nezirim, if one sets aside money for
the קרבנות korbanos of both of them.
Yes, but it has to be sanctified for that person. And this
was money that was sanctified for the father, no, now it was
sanctified for the father and being used by the son.
If they were נזירים nezirim before I think. Okay, if they only
overlap one day, it's enough.
Right? Even to overlap just one day, it's enough.
Right, yeah, yeah, exactly. Now there's a whole question about what the
גרסא girsa is, because according to תוספות, Tosafos, right, according to this
גרסא, girsa, Rabbi Yossi says it only works when they were נזירים
nezirim at the same time, but תוספות Tosafos quotes a completely different
גרסא girsa which is the exact reverse, that Rabbi Yossi says when
they're נזירים nezirim at the same time it doesn't work, it only
works when the son accepts a נזירות nezirus, after the father died.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's
the reason that a son is able to use the father's funds
for his for the son's קרבנות? korbanos? So אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה
היא בנזיר. Amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha hi b'nazir. Okay, is this getting
to sound familiar? Rabbi Yochanan has this stock answer to all these
crazy things, הלכה היא בנזיר. halacha hi b'nazir. I can't tell you
any source, this is this is just the הלכה. halakhah Now interestingly,
almost always Rabbi Yochanan gives another reason, either he quotes a פסוק
pasuk or he says it's חינוך, but here apparently there's no פסוק,
pasuk, no חינוך, nothing else to say, so here ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish is silent, but presumably Rabbi Yochanan is the only answer that
works here because there's no other way to explain this, that that's
just the הלכה. halakhah Okay, פשיטא, p'shita, obviously, מאי למימרא, Mai l'meimra,
that בן יורש את אביו, ben yoresh es aviv, but בת לא.
bas lo.
So now the גמרא's פשיטא p'shita is not so much פשיטא p'shita
on the whole law, but פשיטא p'shita that it's only a son
and not a daughter. Okay, of course, because this gets to this
question about how much is this based on a the normal construct
of ירושה, yerusha, okay, especially if you say that it's that the
son does it after the father, accepts a נזירות after the father
died. So the גמרא says,
obviously, alright, alright, obviously, a son inherits his father not a daughter,
so of course a daughter can't do it. Even if it was
just straight funds she wouldn't be able to get it, certainly not
if they're הקדש hekdesh funds. לא צריכא דלית ליה אלא ברתא. Lo
tzricha d'leis lei ela barta. No, let's say a case that he
only had a daughter, and the daughter would inherit the rest of
his property. מהו דתימא, Ma de-teima, יורשין גמרינן
לה, yorshin gamrinan lah, and so maybe we learn it out from
the concept of ירושה yerusha and the same way she inherits
the other
property. And
our question is, how do you know any of it? Right? The
same way by the question about the father doing it, you know,
making his son a נזיר, how do you know any of it?
And you have to say הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha leMoshe miSinai. But
the גמרא somehow jumps to how do you know a particular aspect
of this, right? Which is both by the father making his son
a נזיר and by this. How do you know only sons and
not daughters? How do you know only fathers and not mothers? Oh,
הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha leMoshe miSinai. All right? But anyway, but again,
what's funny is that before you get to the הלכה למשה מסיני
Halacha leMoshe miSinai to tell you a nuance in this law, you
need the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha leMoshe miSinai to tell you the
whole law to begin with, right? Anyway, fine. But that's what the
גמרא says. According to Rabbi Yochanan it's הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha leMoshe
miSinai that the son can use the father's money. That הלכה Halacha.
tells you also only sons and not daughters, and you need that
חידוש chiddush even in a case where the daughter is the only
child and the daughter would generally inherit the funds.
Yes, and the גמרא wants to broaden and abstract a case from
the משנה Mishnah to other cases. Right. Here it wants to descend,
it's to narrow it to only focus on some small point.
Well, that's because we don't have a general principle, we just have
this sort of arbitrary ruling. Right. So that's part of the nature
of הלכה היא. halacha hi. There's a lot of arbitrary parameters, and
the only way to explain it is that this whole thing is
just really some arbitrary traditional law. Okay. איבעיא להו. Iba'u lehu. Now
here's the question: פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי יוסי או לא פליגי? pligi
rabbanan alei deRabbi Yosi o lo pligi? When Rabbi Yosi says, now
we don't know which one Rabbi Yosi was saying, but let's work
with because this will be consistent with the ברייתא Braisa we're about
to quote, that Rabbi Yosi says it only works if it's the
son, if the son does it after the father dies. So it
quotes Rabbi Yosi saying it. So what presumably there's another opinion out
there, there's a rabbis, you know, so what do the rabbis hold?
Do the rabbis agree with Rabbi Yosi or not agree with him?
אם תימצי לומר פליגי, Im timtzo lomar pligi, if they do argue,
ארישא? areisha? Do they argue on the first case? When he says
what doesn't work, that he says again, we'll go with the version
that he says if they were alive at the same time it
doesn't work. To say they disagree with that and say the same
time does
work. או אסייפא? O aseifa? Or do they also disagree with the
end where he says after the death it does work? And maybe
the rabbis say after the death it doesn't. Right? Because there's two
points here: what does and what doesn't. Right? You could say the
flip. Rabbi Yosi says alive at the same time, again, we'll go
with this version, the version I'm saying, after the death works, alive
at the same time doesn't. If you were to disagree, you could
say the mirror image, right? Or you could disagree with just one
of those הלכות, halachos, say that both of those times work, right?
As opposed to the flip. So that's the גמרא's question.
So, תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear. כיצד אמרו איש מגלח
על נזירות אביו? Keitzad amru ish megaleiach al nezirus aviv? How is
it that a father can use the son can use the father's
money for his sacrifices? מי שהיה אביו נזיר, Mi shehayah aviv nazir,
father was a נזיר, והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו ומת, vehifrish aviv maos
leneziruto umes, father set aside money and he died, ואמר הרי אני
נזיר על מנת שאגלח על מעות אבא, ve'amar harei ani nazir al
mnat she'agaleiach al maos aba, I'll be—so again, this is after the
father died—I'm going to use my father's money. זהו שמגלח על מעות
אביו. Zehu shemegaleiach al maos aviv. That's using the, that's an acceptable
way to use the father's money. אבל מי שהיה הוא ואביו נזירים,
Aval mi shehayah hu ve'aviv nezirim, he and his father were נזירים
nezirim at the same time, והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו ומת, vehifrish aviv
maos leneziruto umes, and then the father set aside money and the
father died, הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה, harei elu yiplu linedavah, then that
goes to a עולה Olah that he cannot use the money, דברי
רבי יוסי. divrei Rabbi Yosi. So according to this ברייתא, Braisa, right,
this is why we I gave you the reverse גירסא girsa of
what we had printed in our משנה, Mishnah because this ברייתא Braisa
has Rabbi Yosi explicitly saying that it only works after the father
died, it does not work if they were at the same time.
So let's assume that's the version in our משנה as well. Okay,
so according to Rabbi Yosi, this idea works only if the son
became a נזיר after the father died, not if it's the same
time. Rabbi Yehuda now but here we get some other voices as
well. רבי אליעזר ורבי מאיר ורבי יהודה אמרו, Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Meir
veRabbi Yehuda amru, זהו
שמגלח על מעות אביו. zehu shemegaleiach al maos aviv. No, in the
case where they were נזירים nezirim at the same time, he also
right, that's from most recent latter case here mentioned in this ברייתא,
Braisa, in the case when they were נזירים nezirim at the same
time, he the son can also use the father's money. Okay, so
that's also okay. So you see they say that when it's at
the same time he can use the father's money. Now does it
mean that they disagree in the first case and they say that
after the father died he cannot? Or you know, are they saying
the exact mirror image? Or are they saying both cases the son
can use the father's money? Not so clear from this ברייתא. Braisa.
Anyway what you do see is, is that you have the range
of positions about whether it's after death, which is now what's Rabbi
Yosi's case, and now presumably that's our גירסא girsa in the משנה
although that's a question, or whether it's only not whether it's okay
Rabbi Yosi is only after death. The question is what's the opposing
position? Is the opposing position also what when they're both alive that
also works? Or is it no... the flip. the exact mirror image,
only when they were נזירים nezirim at the same time does it
work, after death doesn't work. So we have a range of possible
cases. Now the גמרא's going to end by asking some interesting questions
about how much, although this
doesn't fully fit
within the laws of ירושה yerushah because it would not apply to
a daughter, but how much do the laws of ירושה yerushah to
some degree define the parameters? Okay, and that's going to be the
next series of questions. Let's take a look.
Why use the money for their sacrifice? How could the son or
even pay for the for the sacrifice or the daughter, wouldn't wouldn't
that be allowed?
From their own money. No, no, no, no, they no, no, no,
no, first of all they can use their money from their own
bank account. But second of all, I don't know, what are you
talking about? The son's been an investment banker for the last thirty
years and then his father died. I don't understand the question number
one. But number two is we're not talking about minors. Number two
is is that any money you inherit that's not sanctified you can
use for whatever you want. We're talking about the sanctified monies can
only be used, that's the issue. Okay, so now the גמרא says
like this.
Okay, בעא רבה, ba'ei Rabbah, רבה Rabbah asks: יש לו שני בנים
נזירים, yesh lo sheni banim nezirim, the father has two sons who
are נזירים. nezirim. Again, whether this is the version that they were
alive at the same
time and that they were נזירים nezirim at the same time, or
whether it's the version that they became נזיר after the father died,
doesn't matter. Okay, however you work it out, you have two, guy
left two sons and they're now נזירים nezirim and they want to
use the father's funds. Okay, and it would be in a scenario
if it was one son he could use the father's
sanctified funds. מהו, mahu, what's the הלכה halacha about who gets to
use the funds? הלכה גמירי לה, halakhah gemiri lah, כל דקדים גילח
גילח. kol de-kadim gille'ach gille'ach.
Do we say this is not based on ירושה yerushah at all,
it's just an arbitrary הלכה within נזירות and may therefore be, you
know, first come first serve, whoever goes ahead and brings his קרבנות
korbanot first gets to use that money,
first one
to take the money and use it gets the right to use
it? או דלמא, o dilma, or do we say ירושה גמירי לה?
yerushah gemiri lah? No, even if there's a הלכה part to this,
it nevertheless is based on some of the laws of ירושה? yerushah?
ופלגא הוי, u-palga havai,
and each son gets to use half the funds? Okay, so that's
a good question, right? One also wonders what would happen if one
son, let's say it was a case when the kid did it
after the father died. So the father died, one son became a
נזיר and it was his turn to bring the קרבנות korbanot and
the other son said like, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, I'm going
to plan on being a נזיר a month from now, not now,
but I'm planning on it. You only get to use half, right?
If you say they split it, at what stage do they both
have to be נזירים? nezirim? Let's say the other son became a
נזיר twenty days into the first son's נזיר. Let's say the other
son became a נזיר after the son's thirty days were up but
before he brought the קרבנות. korbanot. Like, at what stage does the
second son get a right to say I'm entitled to half these
funds? That the גמרא doesn't explore. No, the גמרא explores an easier
case, they're both נזירים nezirim at the same time. I'm just building
on the גמרא's case, okay? So the first question is if both
נזירים nezirim at the same time, do we fundamentally say the funds
go all to one son who wants to use it, first come
first serve, or do we say that even though this doesn't apply
to daughters, it only applies to sons, but within the category of
sons we are going to be guided by laws of ירושה yerushah
and we're going to say it gets split between the two sons?
Okay, but my only question is what qualifies the both sons as
being entitled within this world of נזירים? nezirim? You know, do they
both have to be נזירים nezirim at the same time? Whatever, that's
to be explored even further. Now we're going to have another variation
of this question. Okay, בעא רבא, ba'ei Rava, רבא Rava asks the
following question: ובכור ופשוט, u-bekhor u-pashut,
let's say one of them is a firstborn son and the other
is a normal son. So the first one gets two portions. מהי?
mai? הלכה גמירי לה, halakhah gemiri lah, הלכך לא בעו גילוחי, hilkhakh
lo ba'u gillechi, לפי מה דשקלי? le-fum de-shakli?
So therefore, do we say this is הלכה and therefore you don't
get to, literally shave, but you don't get to take the
monies for your קרבנות korbanot according to your proportion in the ירושה?
yerushah? Meaning maybe we'll say that fine, the sons split it, but
maybe they don't split it exactly according to ירושה yerushah laws. Even
the בכור bekhor gets only an equal portion. Maybe we say that.
או דלמא ירושה היא? o dilma yerushah hi? No, no, no, we're
going to follow ירושה yerushah laws consistently here. וכי היכי דשקיל פי
שנים הכא נמי מגלה, u-khi heikhi de-shakil pi shenayim hakha nami megalle'ach,
the same way he would get two portions in terms of other
funds, he gets two portions of the funds towards his קרבנות. korbanot.
So how much are we going to even to the degree of
the idea of בכור bekhor follow those laws? ואם תמצא לומר ירושה
היא, ve-im timtza lomar yerushah hi, if we say that it is
going to follow the laws of ירושה, yerushah, ולפום דשקיל מגלה u-le-fum
de-shakil megalle'ach
and he uses the money for his קרבנות korbanot according to his
normal portion of the ירושה. yerushah. ובחולין הוא דאית ליה פי שנים
אבל בהקדש לא, u-ve-chullin hu de-it leh pi shenayim aval be-hekdesh lo,
do we say it's only for חולין chullin purposes and not for
הקדש? hekdesh? או דלמא כיון דקני ליה לגילוחי לא שנא? o dilma
keivan de-kanei leh le-gillu'ach lo shena? Or since it's for the purpose
of shaving and his קרבנות, korbanot, it doesn't matter? Now what does
this mean for חולין chullin or for הקדש? hekdesh? All of this
is for הקדש. hekdesh. All of this is to bring his קרבן.
korban. or no. That's what we're talking about. What's this idea, oh
maybe it's limited to חולין? Chulin? So תוספות Tosafos has one answer
which is very not satisfying, which is he says the difference between
חולין Chulin and הקדש Hekdesh is in one case the guy says
I want to use that money for my נזירות. So he's not
saying explicitly for my קרבנות. Korbanos. So the fact that even though
that's what it winds up meaning, the fact that he frames it
as my נזירות keeps it more in the normal world of ירושה.
Yerusha. But as soon as he says I want to use it
for my קרבנות Korbanos and explicitly identifies it as being קרבנות, Korbanos,
then maybe we don't apply this. And like what difference does it
make? Either way it's the same point. Who cares whether he uses
this word or that word? It's the exact same הלכה. So the
ראש Rosh does not like that answer. If you take a look
at the ראש, Rosh he says the following. He says...
he says like this. ואם תמצא לומר. Im timtze lomar.
It is basically, you see the תוספות Tosafos that says אביב, Aviv,
like in the first wide line of תוספות. Tosafos. Go across from
there and go back down two lines in the ראש Rosh, where
it says ואם תמצא לומר, Im timtze lomar, beginning of a line.
In microscopic letters.
Exactly. ואם תמצא לומר לפומי דשקיל מגלח בחולין הוא דאיתא פי שנים
כגון שאמר אביב אלו מעות לנזירותי ולא לקרבנות נזירותי. V'im timtze lomar
l'fumei d'shakil m'galaiach b'chulin hu d'isay pi shnayim k'gon she'amar aviv 'elu
maws l'nezirosi' v'lo l'korbanos nezirosi.
Oh
no, I'm sorry. It's not that the son said that it's for
the נזירות of the קרבנות, korbanos, it's whether the father said it.
אבל בהקדש לא אם אמר לקרבנות נזירותי. Aval b'hekdesh lo im amar
l'korbanos nezirosi. But maybe it wouldn't apply בהקדש b'hekdesh if the father
explicitly said קרבנות. Korbanos. והוא הדין דמצי מבעיא ליה גם בפשוט. V'hu
din d'mamtzi m'ibaya gam b'pashut. And now the ראש adds, והוא הדין
דמצי מבעיא ליה גם בפשוט, v'hu din d'mamtzi m'ibaya gam b'pashut, we
don't have to ask this question only by the בכור. bechor. We
could have just had it in a general question. איגמיר הלכה במותי
דהקדש. Igmirei halacha b'mosei d'hekdesh.
Does it apply when the father explicitly labeled the money as הקדש?
hekdesh? ופירוש זר הוא. Upirush zar hu. That's a bizarre explanation. Because
besides that the גמרא seems to only be asking it in the
context of a בכור, bechor, what difference does it make if the
father said נזירות or קרבנות נזירות? korbanos neziros? It means the same
thing. He's מקדיש makdish the funds. ויראה לפרש, V'yeira l'fareish, דסיומא דמילתא
הוא, d'siyuma d'milsahu,
that it's ending the discussion of the בכור. bechor. ואם תמצא לומר
ירושה הוא לפומי דשקיל מגלח. V'im timtze lomar yerusha hu l'fumei d'shakil
m'galaiach.
Okay, so if we say that it follows the laws of ירושה
yerusha and it follows the proportion you normally get. דבי פשוטים כל
חד מגלח לפומי דשקיל ולא אמרנו כל הקודם מגלח. D'bei peshutim kol
chad m'galaiach l'fumei d'shakil v'lo meinu kol d'kadim m'galaiach.
So first we say, so fine. By normal laws, sons, you know,
each one gets an equal portion if it's two sons. אחר הכי
אתפרש בכור פשוט לא מגלח או לפומי דשקיל בשאר
נכסים. Achar hachi itparish bechor pashut lo m'galaiach, ur l'fumei d'shakil b'sh'ar
nechasim. Or do we say that fine, that's by two sons. But
if it was a בכור bechor and a פשוט, pashut, then it
would not get two portions. Why? דבכור הוא דשקיל פי שנים. D'bechora
hu d'shakil pi shnayim. When does the בכור bechor get a double
portion?
Meaning, it's one thing to say that the normal kids' הקדש hekdesh
funds get divided according to ירושה yerusha rules. But by the בכור,
bechor, maybe הקדש hekdesh funds would not follow ירושה yerusha rules. Why?
דכתיב ביה בכל אשר ימצא לו. D'ketiv bei 'b'chol asher yimatzei lo'.
Because by the בכור bechor it says he gets double with the
funds the money that is found, that is available. Okay? And that
idea that it's available is less relevant by הקדש. hekdesh. הקדש Hekdesh
isn't really available funds. They're really pre-designated for הקדש. hekdesh. או דילמא
לא שנא. O dilma lo shena. Maybe it doesn't matter. So what
he's saying is, this idea of חולין chulin and הקדש hekdesh is
not a new question. It's sharpening the point about the בכור. bechor.
Even if we normally say it follows ירושה yerusha rules in terms
of dividing the funds, maybe not by בכור. bechor. Why should בכור
bechor be different? That's part of ירושה yerusha rules. No. בכור Bechor
maybe is an idea that's fundamentally is really only relevant to חולין
chulin because בכור bechor has this idea בכל אשר ימצא לו. b'chol
asher yimatzei lo. The funds have to the money has to be
available. But by הקדש, hekdesh, even if there's a rule here that
הקדש hekdesh funds get divided, נזירות הקדש neziros hekdesh funds get divided,
that would not be relevant for בכור. bechor. בכור Bechor fundamentally is
not relevant to the world of הקדש hekdesh because it doesn't satisfy
בכל אשר ימצא לו. b'chol asher yimatzei lo. So according to the
ראש, this question of חולין chulin and הקדש hekdesh is a way
of clarifying why בכור bechor might be different. Okay, let's now read
the last question. אביב נזיר עולם והוא נזיר סתם. Aviv nazir olam
v'hu nazir stam. אביב נזיר עולם והוא נזיר סתם. Aviv nazir olam
v'hu nazir stam.
Let's say he and his father are different types of נזירים. nezirim.
His father's a נזיר עולם nazir olam and he's a נזיר סתם.
nazir stam. Now you'll tell me if his father's a נזיר עולם,
nazir olam, why does he have funds for קרבנות? korbanos? The father's
נזירות is never going to end. Because you'll remember that a נזיר
עולם nazir olam gets to take a haircut once every thirty days
or once every year, but only when he brings the right the
קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so alright. So let's say they're different types of
נזירים. nezirim. Can you reassign the funds from type A to type
B? אביב נזיר
סתם והוא נזיר עולם מאי? Aviv nazir stam v'hu nazir olam mai?
What do we say? הכי גמרינן הלכתא בסתם נזירות. Hi gamrinan hilchasa
bistam neziros. Does it apply just for normal נזירות? או דילמא לא
שנא? O dilma lo shena? Does it not matter? Now you could
also say and תוספות Tosafos says you could also ask the question
if they're both נזיר עולם. nazir olam. Maybe even if they're the
same type, maybe this הלכה only applies to normal נזירות and not
to סתם stam and not to נזיר עולם. nazir olam. But even
if it applies to נזיר עולם, nazir olam, maybe it only applies
when the father and the sons are the same, not where they're
different. ואם תמצא לומר הכא עדי ועדי נזירות טהרה. Im timtze lomar
hacha 'adi v'adi neziros tahara'. אם תמצא לומר הכא אידי ואידי נזירות
טהרה, Im timtza lomar hacha idi ve-idi nezirus tahara, אם תמצא לומר,
im timtza lomar, and if you say no, doesn't matter if the
father's a נזיר עולם Nazir Olam and the son is a נזיר,
is a regular נזיר, they're both טהרה נזירותes, tahara nezirus so you
can apply the funds. But בעא רב אשי: Bayei Rav Ashi: אביו's
Aviv נזיר טמא Nazir Tamei והוא נזיר טהור. ve-hu Nazir Tahor. Let's
say the money was applied for different types of קרבנות. korbanot. Not
just different נזירותes. Different נזירותes, whether נזיר עולם, Nazir Olam, נזיר סתם,
Nazir stam, it's the same animal, same קרבנות. korbanot. But let's say
the father set aside the money because the father had become טמא,
tamei, and then he would have brought different קרבנות, korbanot, birds instead
of sheep and so on, right, and for the purpose of טומאה,
tumah, not for the purpose of any נזירות, and then the father
died. Can the son use it for נזירות טהרה? nezirus tahara? Or
אביו נזיר טהור והוא נזיר טמא, Aviv Nazir Tahor ve-hu Nazir Tamei,
מאי? What about the reverse? תיקו. teiku. So we're going to leave
that with a standing question. והדרן עלך מי שאמר. ve-hadran alach Mi
She'amar. So we successfully actually our full.